I come from Olympic weightlifting,
athletics. I focus always on progress,
and that's what the athletes are about.
When you think about physical
therapists, chiropractors,
we call them recoverers. So, helping us
to recover. Return the person to where
the person was before. With Jerzy,
that's not the case for cerebral palsy
people, because they are already there,
and they cannot return anywhere. So,
they have to
progress the same way as athletes.
>> Jerzy, nice to see you, as always.
>> pleasure.
>> Yeah, all right. I'm going to tell
>> Good to be here.
>> Yeah, I always love spending time with
you, and I have wanted to have this
conversation for, doing the math,
more than 10 years, because you told me
of this transformation that we're going
to be discussing in detail a long time
ago.
And
it blew my mind to the extent that, you
may not remember this, I wanted to try
to figure out a way
to hire a long-form journalist to write
an entire long-form magazine piece on
this, and it turned out
that a much better format is film. And
certainly in this conversation we'll
talk about it, but not to bury the lead.
For people who don't have any context,
Jerzy and I have known each other quite
a long time, and Jerzy's appeared on the
podcast before, alongside Naval
Ravikant,
who also has worked with Jerzy, and
Jerzy's a four-time world weightlifting
champion, co-founder of UCLA's
weightlifting team, co-creator with his
wife, Aniela, the lovely Aniela, of the
Happy Body Program. There's a lot more
to his story. We get into it in depth in
the first conversation. This time
around, we're going to talk about a
very, very specific transformation that
people might not associate
with weightlifting when they envision
lifting weights in the gym and that is
just how far-reaching
coaching transformation
can be. And I'm going to read a
definition first
of cerebral palsy, CP. This is from
the AI answer on Google, but you'll see
some version of this in most places. So,
cerebral palsy is a group of permanent
disorders
affecting movement, posture, and muscle
tone caused by abnormal brain
development or damage to the developing
brain, usually before birth, sometimes
it's during birth.
It is the most common motor disability
in children resulting in non-progressive
limitations.
I'm just highlighting a few words here.
Permanent, non-progressive limitations,
meaning the brain injury does not change
over time on muscle coordination and
balance. All right, now
I'm going to compare that with a lead
into
the doc which I'm making available for
free on YouTube, which is called
Prisoner No More. We'll have more to say
about that. It is quite short, easy to
watch, about 30 minutes to my memory.
Here's the description. What happens
when a doctor's prognosis becomes a life
sentence and one person refuses to serve
it? Prisoner No More follows Tajin Park,
and I recognize that is not probably the
perfect pronunciation for Korean, but
Tajin Park, a young man diagnosed with
cerebral palsy, who dismantled every
physical limitation medical science
predicted for him through elite athletic
training under Olympic strength coach
Jerzy Gregorek and an uncompromising
commitment to identity transformation,
Tajin's story redefines what the human
body and mind are capable of.
And that's directed by Jeff Wolf and we
will come back to that as well.
But
let's hop into an actual conversation
here
and begin with Jerzy, if you wouldn't
mind, just some before and afters,
right? And then we'll go into the entire
chronology of it and everything else.
But maybe we could just touch on a few
like bench press, what he could do
before to gym, and what he could do
after. Math, language, where would you
like to start?
>> Uh, let's start from bench press, I
guess.
>> Okay.
>> So, the first day I loaded the bar 15
lbs, and
he couldn't lift. He couldn't take it
off the rack.
>> Right, he couldn't unrack it.
>> Just only 15 lbs.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I have this wooden bar, Olympic
wooden bar, that I used to coach
children.
>> Mhm.
>> 4-year-olds, 5.
>> I remember my uh daughter was doing
snatches when she was 3 years old.
It's 3 lbs.
>> Mhm.
>> But I put the 3 lbs on,
and he lifted it.
>> Mhm.
>> 3 lbs.
And I thought, "Okay.
He could lift three, so let's see if he
can lift eight." So, I added 5 lbs, and
he did.
>> Mhm.
>> I was surprised. It surprised me.
>> The difference. And then I loaded
another five on, and it was 13, and he
did. Came back to 15 lbs. He barely lift
that, but he did.
>> Mhm.
>> So, that gave me the insight right away
that he is going to progress fast. So, I
asked for his father to come to the gym,
and I told him,
"You have to be here, and you have to
watch every session with him. I guess
something is going to happen here." I
already got that
feelings that something good is going to
happen.
>> So, so I I want to spoil the story.
We're going to get into micro
progressions and certainly the
importance of the bench press which you
identified really early on.
What did he get to as his sort of
maximum working weight in the bench
press?
>> He got to 170.
>> At what body weight?
>> I think around 140. So he passed his
body weight. He became stronger than his
father and his father couldn't believe.
But as the father was
watching it for years
and he said at one point he said
I'm really getting what's the micro
progression is. It's amazing thing.
So that was
really something.
>> So another layer to this story that
makes it all the more amazing and
inspirational and mind-boggling is that
Tejan also is autistic, if I'm correct,
right? So
while you're helping him to build
confidence and competence physically,
you were also working on a lot of other
things and I'm sure we'll get into many
of them, but could you just tell us a
bit more about his conversational
ability before and after?
>> But the father told me that he was
the conversation only with Tejan was
time to go
to bed or time to eat.
And there were some probably more
because he could count to 1 to 10.
And but he wouldn't know what is 3 minus
2.
What I noticed that he needs to work on
the math because
I asked him to to do five squats
and he did six or four, sometimes five.
So I said Tejan
I wanted five.
And said that was five and it was six,
right? So
he was missing. Mhm. that gave me the
idea that
he needs to work on his math.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I started asking him simple
questions. What is 3 + 2? 3 + 5 and
up to 10, he was okay.
>> Mhm.
>> But after 10,
didn't know what is the 5 + 7.
>> Mhm.
>> The subtraction didn't know at all.
So, that was
the beginning of the math. When he
came to English and any conversation,
he couldn't
have any conversation.
So, the
father
after about probably a year, he said we
had a first conversation.
>> After a year of training?
>> Yes, we actually talk about something.
So, that was amazing. Yeah.
>> How long did you train with
Tijan?
>> Almost 5 years.
>> Okay. So, at the end of 5 years with
math,
where was he?
>> Well, he's in community college. He
passed 57 units.
>> Mhm.
>> So, he is waiting for another three
units to
finish 60 and go to San Jose State.
So, you can you can imagine what his
math is and English, he writes essays
and
>> So, let that sink in, people. It is so
wild and you'll see this in the video,
to not just converse about concrete
objects, right? The mug in front of us
or
something to the left of us, the dog on
the floor, but you had him memorize
poetry so you could discuss things like
emotional tone,
metaphor,
right? Getting into much more
complicated
terrain.
And honestly, the more I
learn about this and the more I revisit
it because this is not the first time
we've talked about this.
>> Right.
>> And I I just rewatched the documentary
earlier today in which I did the
voiceover for.
And
I got really emotional watching it to be
honest. So, I want to talk about the how
to because there's so many so many
pieces to this. But maybe what we should
talk about is
why previous
approaches hadn't worked, right? How are
people with cerebral palsy generally
treated? Right? By society, why do they
have these deficiencies, right? The lazy
explanation is well, they have these
this brain damage or abnormal brain
development and that's that, right? It's
a sentence.
>> And then Tijen had worked with physical
therapists before meeting you. So, like
why didn't he make progress? I mean,
those are two different questions, but
I'll let you start with maybe how you
view the environment and society as
implicated in
the development for people with cerebral
palsy. And this applies to many other
places by the way. It's not limited to
cerebral palsy.
But for instance, we were talking about
community college and Tijen when he
decided to go back to school, which
didn't start with college, of course.
And there were a lot of pressures to put
him into a special program. And you were
like, no. No special program. Like he
has to be around normal kids.
So, I'm I'm leading into it a little
bit, but would you like to say a bit
more about that?
>> I come from Olympic weightlifting, as
you know. So, athletics.
Uh focus always on progress and reaching
records, breaking records. And that's
what the athletes are about.
But when you think about physical
therapists, chiropractors,
doctors,
we call them really in weightlifting
recoverers.
>> Mhm.
>> So, helping us to recover, acupuncture,
massage, and all of this is when we do
the training,
we need recovery.
>> Mhm.
>> So, the recovery is that system that
helps us to
recover the body for the next day
and do the next day something a little
bit more than before.
>> Mhm.
>> And I create the progress.
When
physical therapist approach, let's say,
uh somebody that is after surgery or has
problems,
the mission is to return the person to
where the person was before.
>> Mhm.
>> And the same with doctors,
make them healthy again.
>> Mhm.
>> But
with Tajam, this is not the case
because all cerebral palsy people,
because they are already there.
>> Mhm.
>> And they cannot return anywhere.
>> Right.
>> So, they
have to
progress the same way as athletes.
Forward.
More.
You know, either stronger, faster.
What is 5 + 7?
>> Mhm.
>> Or write a line, memorize the poem.
So, all of it and, you know, belief
system that you took
before that then triggers here too
because he hated
the son, the son.
>> Mhm.
>> And he hated police, and he hated
mother. He had father, and and that came
out during our process of coaching.
So, that I had to address, too. So, all
the philosophy was also the part of it.
It was poetry, philosophy, there was
math, and there was English.
But, uh coming back to what you said
about the whole
community that works with cerebral
palsy, I think that they the focus is
not athletic focus.
The focus is to comfort them.
So, not really improve them.
>> Mhm.
>> Not to improve them so they are
improving.
>> Mhm.
>> Just to comfort them so they have their
safety life and
they okay.
>> Mhm.
>> I guess that that's probably the
difference here.
>> And just to reiterate something for
people who are listening, right? We're
talking about in in some respects two
things that will get intermingled as we
talk,
which does not mean that we're equating
them, but you have on one hand sort of
the mood affect and some of the
communication challenges and
other components of autism spectrum
disorder.
Then you have the motor challenges
and much more, of course, related to
cerebral palsy.
So, we're talking we're talking about
both.
And let's revisit the prior physical
therapist, right? Because I believe,
based on some of the notes that you sent
to me,
that his approach was to put
Tijan on a treadmill.
Is that right? Or you just There was In
other words, it was
>> And he hated it.
>> He threw him into a plan, but it wasn't
a progression.
I don't know if that's fair to say. I
mean, maybe maybe there was minimal
progression to it, but
>> Yeah, maybe some progression of a
treadmill, but a treadmill after a while
creates exhaustion,
>> Mhm.
>> tiredness, and the brain actually
becomes depleted
>> Mhm.
>> instead of getting the power, getting
the strength, getting more energy. We're
talking about a resting energy.
>> Mhm.
>> And when that resting energy can be
improved,
that resting energy can keep the person
awake. He was very lethargic at the
beginning.
>> Yeah, he'd sleep in the car. He would
sleep whenever he had a moment to sleep.
>> never was awakening the car. And when he
was in the room,
he would usually sleep because
he was not engaged with people.
>> Mhm.
>> So, he was sleeping.
>> And so, the bench press
seems like it was one of the
kind of key components to increasing
resting energy.
>> Yes, bench press, uh squats.
>> What type of squats?
>> Back squats.
>> Back squat.
>> Back squat and then eventually the back
squat
was big challenge because he couldn't
sit down.
>> Mhm.
>> He was very stiff.
Because he was stiff, he would fall on
daily basis. He was bruised all over the
body.
And he walk awkwardly.
>> Mhm.
>> Usually father hold his hand and when
they were walking and he was just
walking very very to the left, to the
back, and then awkwardly. So, that
created a challenge. So, the challenge
for the squatting was that he was not
able to squat down. He was able to bend.
>> Right. Which is why his parents also
took him to the bathroom
>> was looking Yeah, he was looking for the
box or the chair. You remember the boxes
there.
>> I do. Yeah.
>> So, he was not able to set to sit on a
20-in box
because he was bending forward and
looking for the box. So, that was about,
I guess, at the beginning about 20-in 23
in.
When it came to 16 in, I noticed that he
is nicely squatting down. And also was
able to turn. At the beginning, he was
not able to turn.
So, when I noticed that,
I told the dad,
"He's ready to go to the restroom on his
own
and ready for the other things in the
restroom." So, and that was the
beginning of
the first really independence
>> Mhm.
>> for Tejan. He was able to dress himself.
The other thing was to tie the
shoelaces.
>> Mhm.
>> So, at a certain point, I saw that he
has this
shoes and uh his shoelaces were untied.
And the father run
to tie his shoes, right?
I said, "No, no, no. You can do that."
And
I said, "Okay." So, father sat uh
outside of near our lunches in the
house. And so, he bent and he tried to
tie. And the father was looking,
piercing, you know?
I said, "Relax. Relax. He's going to be
okay." And I created this atmosphere
facilitated for Tejan, so he could
relax.
>> Mhm.
>> And he could actually make it happen. It
was about 20 minutes before he actually
made it, but it was a torture for the
father.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I started really seeing how the
parents are with him. That I had to
teach the father, the mother to be
patient, to wait until he does
something, not to do for him. So, that
was also element that was needed to be
fixed.
>> It's also, and looking at it through
very sympathetic lens, I can understand
how
all three of them have been
struggling and working hard to do the
best they can over
How old was Tejan when you when you met
him?
>> 25.
>> They weigh in tons.
>> So, 25 years, right? Of conditioning and
habits. So, it takes
time for everybody involved to change
the habits.
>> taking bomb.
>> Yeah.
>> They were so intense
with him.
And he was, I would say, so fast
respond. And his
also walk was that way. He tried to walk
fast because he
believed
then walking fast
he will be normal.
Right?
But I slowed down everything. I taught
him how to walk and it was the torture
for him, but you know, said, "Heel and
toe and heel."
After about 2 3 years, he started
walking normally, heel and toe and I
know I have a video I sent you a video
of it. It was just amazing to watch that
hand to walk with soft arms because the
his arms were really up and and really
contracted, yeah. And control, extremely
controlled. And then everything started
being more soft and relaxed and and he
started walking
like, you know, like a normal person
what the father wanted.
Came to one of my birthdays and
it was just amazing to see him after
about 4 years
people were just
you know
puzzled and I was, you know, it was just
like, "Is it the same person, really?
What happened to Tadzhan?" It was just
like amazing.
>> So, I'd love to highlight a few of the
ingredients that
were critical for the recipe that led to
that. Because
friend of mine
I'll name him cuz it's funny. He'll get
a good laugh out of it. I remember I
introduced my friend Mike to you and
Mike has very
is a multitude of issues with his hips.
He has one titanium hip. And I remember
I introduced the two you, he came over
and you guys trained. He you laid out a
program for him.
And he was he was unable to squat
properly to a
to a certain depth, so
you meet people where they are, right?
Everybody can improve, but it's about
knowing the starting point. You're
famous for saying this.
And so, you gave him a certain depth,
and I remember he
He did that for maybe a week, and then
he was feeling good, so he decided to do
it, you know, 5 in deeper or something
like that. And he came back and met with
you, and your response
was, "You are wasting both of our time."
Because the micro progressions are
a key component to progressing without
injury. And also, I know that you feel
like the no pain, no gain approach to
training is a myth, right? Or that
belief undergirding training. So, I want
to mention just a few other things, and
they are
of course, all in line with your most
famous mantra of hard choices, easy
life, easy choices, hard life.
Hard doesn't necessarily mean painful,
right? But it does mean hard or
difficult.
But I want to mention a few of them
here, because it's so comprehensive.
We'll come back to this, but
the car spotting,
right? So, Toj
was so lethargic, as we already noted,
that he was typically sleeping, but
after 6 months or so,
you asked his father if he noticed
anything new, and he remarked that Toj
had noticed a car on the way over. So,
you started to give him assignments to
remember the cars that he spotted, the
color, the make, whether the driver was
male or female. And you got an inkling
of his potential for math because he
started memorizing the license plates,
which is just incredible.
Then, negativity, right? This sort of
negative affect. You already mentioned
him hating the sun, hating the police,
hating this, that, or the other thing.
At certain points, hating the workout,
which maybe we'll come back to, because
the I I thought it was very clever how
you responded to that with, "Well, once
you're an adult, you can decide if you
want to quit the training." And you had
>> And that was a trick.
>> you had Yeah, it was a trick and you had
hurdles for hitting that.
>> Yeah.
>> You also gave him assignments though to
come back to the negativity having
dialogues and asking him questions to
see the world more objectively. So,
assignments having writing English and
explain why the sun and the peace might
be important for our existence.
The use of celebrations. I might ask you
about this, but having certain
milestones for him where you would give
him a certificate and then I think it
was later on going to restaurants with
his family and giving it to him in front
of them, but also because his his life I
suppose seemed so perhaps to him
uneventful up to that point like nothing
was happening.
Maybe you could speak a little bit to
that and then I'll jump into some of
these others.
>> Well, you know, his brain was virgin.
>> Mhm.
>> So, nothing was there.
>> Yeah.
>> So, he didn't have history.
>> Mhm.
>> So, he couldn't really talk
about whatever he was doing. He was not
doing anything.
>> Right, there's no content.
>> to create, you know, history in his
mind.
Create memory about something.
>> Mhm.
>> So, one of the things was to give him
certificates for the breaking records.
So, whenever he broke the record
then
we you know, printed diploma
and I asked father to set up a dinner
celebration.
And every time
a record was broken in the squad or
bench press, we went for a dinner.
During this dinner, we gave him diploma
and some other people came and it was
the celebration. And the gentleman
started liking this was like a a star
and
and after
about a year I saw him he started
talking about this celebration. He
talked about math. He talk about poems
and so all of it
start becoming his
memory, his history. It was very
important. And
he also
start liking breaking records.
He got crazy on
jumping on the box, but that came
because you know, he wanted to be an
adult. So
>> Okay, so we're going to we're going to
get to the
>> I
>> the adulthood that might come up
immediately. I also just want to give
credit where credit is due to
the parents and I don't know to what
extent it was both parents or the
father, but driving twice a week. How
how long was the commute each way?
>> So they were coming twice a week about 1
hour and a half driving one way. So
they had to have at least 4 hours
>> Yeah.
>> to come. Father was devoted.
>> Very
kind,
devoted,
and
stoic.
>> Mhm.
>> You know, he was there all the time.
And
you
couldn't really see any irritation in
him at all. Loved his son.
>> Mhm.
>> That was very clear.
So he was coming every time when he
couldn't come, his mother brought him
in. But it was
for them 4 hours
>> That's right.
>> And I was uh I discussed that with Tejan
and I
told Tejan
how
devoted was his father. Eventually when
we started having conversation,
philosophical conversation, appreciative
conversation.
So I try to pass on him the appreciation
of his
father.
Enlarge the imagination about his father
if the father was not committed to that
for 5 years
to bring his son
twice a week
and every time spend 4 hours and the
money
>> Mhm.
>> then
I told to John, you wouldn't be who you
are today.
He helped you to become
what you are.
>> How did he respond to that?
>> Did John, you know, was
interesting he was just sometimes look
and you could see that he
was thinking about something. Sometimes
he
like it
but the joy the most joy that I saw in
him
he was breaking the records and some
VIDEOS ARE THERE.
HE WAS SO joyous like when you see
children sometimes.
Very joyous.
in that moment that nothing else
happens.
>> Yeah.
>> And he was ecstatic, you know. It was
just so
pleasurable to see.
>> Yeah, or like an athlete winning gold at
the Olympics on the platform, you know.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Let's talk as promised about
responsibility and adulthood.
It was a crafty
strategy on your part. Could you could
you speak to that?
>> Well,
he didn't want to play piano first.
>> Because he had been
>> Some
>> required to take piano lessons.
>> Yeah, yeah, so father told him to play
piano and I said he didn't like to come
to the workout and training. He didn't
like the training.
>> So, he didn't like the piano and he
didn't like the training.
>> Yeah, and he said I want to stop the
piano and
and I said, well, you know
you're not an adult so you cannot do it.
You know, somebody needs to decide for
you but when you become an adult you can
stop the piano, You don't have to come
here for the training.
Mhm.
I said, "Well, you know,
then what is the adult, right?" So, we
started discussing. Yeah, so what do you
think? And then he started discussing
what is the really an adult. So, I said,
"Well, you know, adult is independent."
What does it mean independent, right?
So,
working, making money, living somewhere
separately, and so on and so
But then, I said, "But there there's
other thing that we can consider you an
adult.
If you jump on an 18-in box, right?"
So, he was jumping at that time around
11, 12 box.
>> Oh, 11, 12 in?
>> Yeah. He will got so excited.
And he thought that he can conquer it,
right? Very quickly.
And he was on a mission with this box, I
tell you. Now, he was like energy that
was generated in him.
>> Mhm.
>> Wow, this is the same energy like in me
when I was wanted to go to Olympics,
right? It's like I would run to the
forest, you know, 2:00 a.m. Whatever was
needed to do, I would do. And I would do
with
lots of, you know, energy and and and
this is commitment and
So, he was committed.
>> Mhm.
>> He wanted to jump.
But I knew that 6 in
it will take 2 years.
His micro progression
is that. He was not going to do it
easily. But we were on and we are on and
on.
And then, he came to I think about like
17 something inches. He was so excited.
And then, we ended up with some problems
and had to heal his back because it's
not so simple to just jump on an 18.
This is a challenge He a huge challenge
for me.
>> When people watch the documentary, and I
would have mentioned this in the
introduction, but I made a a short link.
Doesn't sound short, but easy to
remember link that'll point you straight
to it on YouTube. If you just go to
tim.blog/hardchoices.
If you go to tim.blog/hardchoices, it'll
take you straight to the doc. But when
you watch the doc, and you look at
Dijan's before, right? What is motion
motor control walking looked like
before, and imagine him jumping onto a
17-in box.
It is unimaginable when you look at the
starting point.
Really just incredible.
Now,
I want to
hear you explain another
development that
I think it's just
so compelling, and that is related to
math. That's
He starts memorizing license plate
numbers. You're also working with him on
repetitions and building up some of that
arithmetic muscle.
How did he go from that to doing math 5
to 6 hours a day, and having that fire
lit with him?
>> Well, it was progressive. But
>> Right, it was progressive, but that's
why I'm asking. How did he get there?
>> So, first I
I started really working on
the counting. So, he had to count from
until 20 or 30.
>> And I'm I'm so sorry to interrupt. I
just want to pause to just let people
have that sink in for a second. Math 5
to 6 hours a day, which again, we're
going to talk about the journey. Like
most people on 20 cups of coffee a day
could not do 5 to 6 hours of math a day.
>> I asked him about the counting.
First it was the counting. That he
couldn't count to 20. So, I said, "Okay,
let's count to 15. Can you count to 15?"
So, we counted to 15. When he got to 15,
I said, "You go home and you start
learning to count to 20." So, he came
back and I tested him. Did you count to
20? Yeah. So, okay, count. So, he
counted. So, then I add the addition,
you know, how much is, you know, 5 + 7?
He wouldn't know. So, homework. Going
homework, you learn how much is 5 by 6,
7, and 8, 9. All the calculation up to
20 for the adding. Then subtraction,
division, multiplication. All of that
until, you know, the number 10 or 20.
Then counting to 30, 40, 50, 100. And
when we got there,
I told that he needs a tutor.
We need a tutor, math tutor, and English
tutor. He needs both.
And so, they hired
people to help. So, I was testing,
of course, but he had these tutors. So,
I think that
it was an amazing
addition
to work on his brain.
And I noticed the same story with others
around policy people that
have difficulties with math.
And some of the times that I
saw that they
had good English,
but math looks like uh
difficulties.
So, eventually, when he progressed with
energy, with bench press, came to the
certain point within a year
that he could press about 100 lb.
And that
gave him enough energy
that he could go to his computer
and spend hours on
the computer
to study his elementary school.
He started actually elementary school.
And you know, because he was not in
elementary school, so he was 25 years
old when he was sick. So, he joined this
program
elementary school program and he
started, you know, working through it on
his own.
And after 2 years, he passed
the whole elementary school.
Then he started high school.
Another 2 years and he passed.
Normal high school, I know like a normal
the same program as other people do.
And father said
Eugene is like on fire.
He's like it's 2:00 a.m. and he's still
on his computer. And he started like
8:00 p.m. and at 2:00 a.m. he's on his
computer and he doesn't want to stop.
It was something in him awaken
and
powerful.
And at the same time, he started
noticing that
who he was as a person.
That actually he was a person.
And he was cerebral palsy.
And that generated a lot of negativity
in him, a lot of
resentment to
to his father and mother and then he
started really talking that he hates his
mother and then he hated everything at
that time. Yeah.
>> And more, yeah.
What did you notice in
And just to flash forward, right? I
mean, he's
his father's reported that he's living
an independent existence, taking care of
his own needs, planning his own days,
orders Uber rides to get to his classes,
manages his own paperwork. So,
that's the that's the after. What did
you notice in terms of and how did you
cultivate this if you did? I don't know
if you did this deliberately or if it
was a byproduct of everything else, but
emotional range or facial expressions.
Did any of those
Did any of that change over the course
of the training?
>> Well, emotionally, he was blank, the
same. So, for a long time.
>> You mean in whatever circumstances?
>> Yeah, but at certain point, he started
being negative and expressing his
negativity.
And then he
he made these moves and
I couldn't see
where he was. I was looking for where he
was, but I
I addressed negativity as something that
needed to be fixed.
So, whenever he
said that he hated something, I
challenged it. Challenged it
in a way, why is it good?
Right?
So, he was negative, but and then why
police is good. Why
the sun is good.
Why the father is good, why the mother
is good. So, expanding and expanding
imagination for him
to facilitate this so he could find in
his mind actually acceptance that
actually is a good thing.
It's a huge shift in his
psych believing and
and liking people, right? He never liked
me. He was just like
I don't like you and he says, I don't
like you. He just says that.
>> How long When he say that for?
>> All the time. He has never liked me.
>> So, he'll celebrate and give you a high
five here at training, but
still
>> I don't know even today if he likes me.
Probably not.
You know,
I I created a lot of hard choices for
him, so he went out You know, eventually
he will come to this point that he will
maybe like what I done, maybe, but not
really maybe.
>> Oh, wow. That's kind of amazing.
Uh well, you know what? As as long as
you don't care about the credit, you're
doing good work in the world, I guess.
>> I was not, you know, there to
>> Yeah.
>> to shine, you know.
>> Of course. Of course. Could you talk
about helping him or asking him to
identify heroes
a bit?
That also
stuck out to me. Could you provide a
little bit of context to people on that
piece?
>> So, he was already in elementary school.
And he was
writing an essay about a hero.
>> That was an assignment.
>> Yes. And he wrote it. So, he was from
school, not from you. Yeah, yeah, from
school. Because he already had that
tutor, English tutor.
So, he was always proud when he did
something. He was bringing something and
and reading me
So, you know,
he
read it.
And
so, he wrote about Genghis Khan.
>> Mhm.
>> And I said, "Okay, so is Genghis Khan a
hero?"
Yeah.
Okay, so I said, "Well, why he is a
hero?"
Uh he talked a little bit, and I said,
"So, who is a hero?"
Well, that created a philosophical
approach. So, we
ended up that the hero is really risking
their own life
for others, to save others.
But that's not Genghis Khan. So, Genghis
Khan was not that. He was a conqueror,
but he was not a hero.
And then, at the same time, I watched
this movie about Admiral, actually
Korean Admiral. About 300 Japanese ships
were coming to Korea to, you know,
conquer them. And he, with one ship and
12, and he stood up to them. And
actually, the 12 ships, you know, the
people didn't want to fight, wanted to
surrender. He said, "No." And he fought,
and he fought. And these other 12 ships,
you know, joined him eventually, and the
whole armada, Japanese armada, turned
back.
>> Mhm.
>> And I said, "That is your hero."
>> Mhm. Yeah.
>> And I said, "That is your hero from
Korea, and you are going to
rewrite this essay. But it's too late."
I said, "It's not too late. You're going
to go to your teacher.
You tell the teacher
why Genghis Khan was not a hero,
and you want to rewrite the essay."
>> Okay.
>> I said, "Okay. You go and do it." And he
did. And he rewrote
the essay. The teacher agreed.
>> I can see why he might not like you.
>> Yeah.
>> It's just
>> It's Yeah. Yeah.
>> fair.
>> It was It was very quick, you know. You
know, you you know, people
>> Well,
>> Well, I I was coaching him. It was He
was
jumping. He was lifting. And at the same
time, we did poetry, math, English,
write all of it together.
And it was
>> Yeah.
>> quick.
>> Hard teachers he didn't like you.
>> wasn't like me, I don't know. Yeah.
There are many reasons. But you know, uh
one day he was he wanted to step on the
6-in box, I remember. And he tries to
step, and he would not.
>> And this is the one foot up
>> Just slipping one foot and like on a
stair, right? It was like he he was
and then like I couldn't make it.
So, I grabbed his shirt
and pulled him.
>> I've seen the video.
>> In and out. And after about two times, I
left him, and he was
jumping on this box like one of the
others stepping one one one
and so fast. It's just amazing what the
brain is.
>> Yeah.
>> You get a little bit help, and suddenly
the door opens up, and it's the
progression is huge and fast. It's
amazing. I tell you what I was watching,
what I learned during this process. Wow.
>> Yeah, I just even to this day, I know
that modern science has come to a
greater appreciation of brain plasticity
and the malleability and adaptability.
And of course, just as the
let's call it broadly speaking, this is
a simplification, but the control center
for the entire body, right? The brain's
job is to keep the body alive. So,
they're they're dance partners.
There is just so much room for
improvement. And
I mean, a lot of the science that I've
supported has been related to this, but
it This was the first time I'd ever seen
such an amazing transformation in
someone with cerebral palsy
that was so clearly and well documented
also, right?
And
I want to talk about next steps in a
little bit
to try to
expand this into a study. But, before we
get there, can you speak to
training logic?
So, I think that was after about 2 years
of already training with him, but
working on his thought process using
poetry.
Why did you do that?
He couldn't really read the lines of
poetry and understand the feelings
emotions behind.
So,
then
I started really doing the math and
seeing whether he can
think logically.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? So, I
tested him, you know, if A is B and B is
C, so is A is also C and
and playing these games.
And
slowly he started not only being logical
in
I asked him about writing something
about what is logic and give me the
example. And so, he was he would bring
me
was there logic or not? So, we tested
that.
And then added the math. But the most
difficult for him was to read the line
of poetry
and know the metaphor.
Not really what really happened, but
what was the meaning of the line.
>> not just the words.
>> Yeah. And every line. So,
when I asked him to remember and recite
the poem, he would recite the poem. And
then we analyze the poem every line.
Line after line. And what is the
meaning? What is the feeling of the
line?
And that was
an amazing
possibility for him to learn the
language and the feeling feelings behind
the language, the emotions.
At the beginning, he didn't have any
clue about the feelings.
What the
actually written words express
when it comes to feelings.
>> Yeah, when I
think about
your entire coaching experience with
Tuganym, struck by
how many different levers
you were you were able to help him pull,
right? But one that sort of meta lesson
that pops out to me, and I'd love for
you to
correct this if I'm not thinking about
it the right way,
is that
he didn't respond to people
in conversation, right? Didn't have much
of a response.
In part, and I'm projecting here,
because he didn't have the belief that
he could. He had no history to support
the belief that he could. Right? And
then with physical movement,
similar, right? And you gave the
example, I mean, this is a very fast
example, but of grabbing the shirt and
kind of forcing him to do it, and then
within a few repetitions, you let go,
and he's doing it on his own. And of
course, there's the progression over
time, but even with the poetry and
how you gave him assignments to practice
public speaking, without that,
he wouldn't have had the confidence to
then speak, say, within the more
complicated context of school with
classmates and things like that. I have
to imagine, right? But
you know, I sometimes have listeners or
readers ask me, "What can I read to
develop more confidence?" And I'm like,
"Well,
you can try to read to develop more
confidence, but really, like, you're not
going to fool yourself. You need to do
things to develop
the history of doing things so that you
have confidence."
Does that resonate, or would you add or
reframe that somehow?
>> You know, yeah, of course, you know,
what
what you say is a certain perspective,
but I would like to tell you about my
perspective.
>> Yeah, that's why I'm asking.
>> You know, I saw the mind, the brain
as something that needs to
find a way forward and find the way
around those patches that
were that.
>> Mhm.
>> And I saw it everywhere. I saw it in
math when
you cannot know what is 2 + 2, that is
4, and you struggle.
You know, for me the child struggles to
find out what is 2 + 2. Eventually
the child knows. And there are so there
are certain connections already.
And then 2 + 3 and so on. Right? So
development of math I so crucial here,
very important. That
when I am not there, he can practice
actually the math. And by practicing the
math, we overcome this
you know, many steps. The steps of
progression, the micro progression.
And also that challenge has this
plasticity of the brain.
That that plasticity is not
you know, like I thought, okay, I make
him strong doesn't mean that something
else is going to happen. Or
maybe I will not make him strong because
the math is not developed.
So I saw the connection between
the the squat, the bench, the numbers,
the words, and the beliefs and
philosophy.
I saw connections everywhere, and I
created the challenges, the hard choices
every time.
Everywhere. For me, you know, bench
pressing
going from 100 lb to 102
was not different than to know what is
15 + 17. If I know what is 15 + 17 is an
another thing that when it happens,
something happened in the brain that was
not there before.
And I
started facilitating all this
development of the brain
that would be challenged, develop
from different perspective. And I think
that eventually the research
is to be done. You know, I try to
understand what I've done because I've
never really work
with person like that, right? So, I try
to understand, too, what happened there,
how did it happen, and whether there
there is possibility even
to replicate this and help, you know, so
many people. Taj's progress is amazing,
crazy, amazing,
>> Mhm.
>> magical.
And if
that could be replicable, wow, we could
help a lot of people.
>> talk about it because before we start
recording, I was trying to get an idea
of the rough number of
cerebral palsy diagnoses in the US. And
you're based in Northern California, so
I wanted to get an idea in California.
These are real back of the napkin rough
internet responses, but it seems like,
let's call it
roughly 1 million diagnoses in the US,
potentially, and then
could be occurrences, not diagnoses, but
somewhere between
100 and 120,000 in California alone. So,
this is a non-trivial condition. It's
very prevalent and
if you could develop a method, right,
through doing research, develop a method
that you mentioned could be replicated,
could be taught to physical therapists,
then
this could have
tremendous impact on a wide scale. And
maybe we could talk about what some of
your thoughts are. And I'm going to
create a web form for people who want to
potentially indicate interest in certain
facets of this.
But, what might what might the program
look like? How many How many patients
would you have?
What would it look like in practice to
do a research project to determine if
you can formulate a method that would be
replicable, or a template maybe with a
little bit of tweaking here and there
that physical therapists could use or
others?
>> Meantime, I had some experience with
others with our policy, EPO. And my
approach is one, I believe that
everybody
can improve.
So, it really doesn't matter for me if
it's cerebral palsy or not.
>> Mhm.
>> If it's chronic fatigue,
it can happen.
>> Mhm.
>> If it's fibromyalgia,
the progress can happen. So, with
cerebral palsy,
when we think about cerebral palsy,
people they have different conditions,
different beginnings.
The most important is to find where is
the beginning?
Where to start?
There's a
one of the major thing because
usually I think that we want too much.
>> Mhm.
>> It's not going to happen. So, we need to
find this
very tiny thing.
You remember Jewel in Hawaii? You helped
me to go and
coach her.
>> Mhm.
>> She was 18 at that time, and she
couldn't control her head and arms and
legs.
So, her mother would hold her, and I
would try to find out where is the
beginning with her.
>> Mhm.
>> And she has hands like this, and and it
was moving, and
and I found out that I pointed to one
place. I took a ball very close to her,
like about an inch from her arm and then
and fingers, and asked her to touch it.
>> Mhm.
>> And she struggled and struggled
and we found a way where actually she
could touch and then she was so happy
>> Mhm.
>> when she touched. Oh, I have to send you
these videos.
>> Yeah, please.
>> You can cry, you know, when you can see
things like this.
And
her joy
when she was doing So,
also the mouth I found out that her mind
was very good with stories. She could
talk about some things and she loved the
stories to listen to stories.
But her mouth was not really different
than the chance.
>> The mouth?
>> Yeah, that was like she could only count
from 1 to 10.
And then
adding, you know, 2 + 5 she would and
then we would start with that. So,
I see the mouth
is major part of
that method.
The physical
is
is of course the beginning.
The beginning is how strong they are
and how flexible they are. Flexibility
is the main point here because the
awkwardness comes from both.
One thing that the brain, the mind
cannot control those places but those
places also the the parts of the body
became that way.
>> Mhm.
>> So, that's why awkwardness is coming in.
So, the the physical
and the physical improvement of the
physical
becomes challenging because
they can, you know, injure themselves.
They can be in pain.
And those two who will facilitate they
will need to know how to start.
>> Mhm.
>> How to use the micro progression, how to
write everything down. Like the gen knew
all his numbers. He knew how to measure
the time of, you know, five or 10 jumps
and
he would write all the
the jumps and brought to the gym what he
did. His homework was numbers, numbers,
numbers, numbers. Not only the numbers
of counting, but also the numbers of
measure.
>> Mhm.
>> Right?
>> So, just to hop in for a second, cuz I
would love to help.
Of course, that's part of the reason
we're doing this conversation is to help
facilitate
trying to create some type of template
that can be applied to a lot of people
with cerebral palsy.
So, the the short link, not to bury the
lead, the short link will just be
tim.blog/cp
and we'll have a web form for people who
may want to
help from an academic perspective,
ideally in Northern California,
somewhere within near driving distance,
since you would want to be there, I I
think the thought is maybe twice a week
with these
different folks, something like that.
>> Yeah, I see that about maybe five
cerebral palsy people.
>> Mhm.
>> And meeting them twice a week.
Let's say Tuesday and Friday.
>> Mhm.
>> For 1 year and then
add another five.
>> Mhm.
>> So, now it's 10.
Another five.
>> Mhm.
>> And do it for
5 years.
>> 5 years in total.
>> Yeah. Record everything. See how it
works.
Bring
therapists or others that could actually
watch, observe, and learn.
>> Mhm.
>> And I
believe
that
is
replicability is possible.
We need to test it.
We need to explore
whether
how is it really possible. What can we
actually do
>> Mhm.
>> when we have this,
you know, 25 people
It could be that it was because I was
there, but I don't want to say it that
it was because of me everything
happened. It could be that perfect storm
happened because I remember I was a math
teacher.
I'm a poet.
>> Mhm.
>> I'm a weightlifter.
So,
so all of it it happened that I was this
one person facilitating that.
>> Mhm.
>> But when we do research, we don't have
to have one person. We can have, you
know, math people, English, and, you
know, philosophers, and we can have
trainers. We can create a center, and in
that center
we can
think about how we can progress.
>> Mhm.
>> How we can improve
and document everything in details the
same way
as I was doing. Micro progression
is an amazing power.
>> Mhm.
What strikes me also that
with the right people involved and with
the right consistency, right? And I
mean, you might need a faculty member to
agree to spearhead it, and then
there would be fundraising, which, you
know, is pretty straightforward to
figure out, and then they would have
post-docs or people underneath them who
would help with recruitment, although I
don't think that'll be a problem after
this podcast.
Patient recruitment, and then making the
trains run on time.
But I could see
a path, as I'm sure you've thought about
this
much more than I have, but where you
could end up with something like a core
curriculum of principles, right? That
you're teaching, and maybe you're
recording video modules to explain these
things to practitioners, where it's like
micro progressions,
finding a place to start. What are
different ways to find a place to start?
And then perhaps there's certain things
that won't apply to everyone. So, for
instance, we didn't talk about We don't
have to spend a lot of time on it, but
Tejan was kind of crumpled to the right
side, right? So, you had a ball hanging
from the ceiling that you would have him
reach up to touch to help correct that.
So, there might be core curriculum and
principles and then sort of ancillary
principles and techniques that can be
applied on a case-by-case basis, but
then you end up with this
core curriculum
that people can learn remotely or
something like that. I mean, it's it's
really exciting to think about.
>> At this point, I see that we can assess
these people from
five perspectives, I think.
The physical perspective, you know,
where they are physically,
and where is the flexibility, where is
the strength. Math perspective,
language perspective, philosophy
perspective, beliefs perspective, where
they are. So, easily we can take the
psychology and then psychologists and
develop certain ways of assessing them.
Where are beliefs, right? Uh in math is
very clear, right? In the language, you
need probably English teachers and they
will
create very quickly curriculum to find
out where is the level of that. And then
once we have the assess, okay,
we have
a physical problem that is 80%
math is only
3% is not, you know, the person is
really good in math in English as well.
But we can have also that
math is not there at all, and walking is
good. So, there are all possibilities
how we can assess
from these five perspectives these
people. But
But we need also explore and experience
them. Right? This you know, not only one
person to join because it's just only
one person. Now, we need to see can we
actually do a five?
Can we actually deliver what we
delivered?
>> I mean, this is the scientific method,
right?
And you've such a fantastic starting
point, right? It's an N of one, although
you you've worked with more than one
person with cerebral palsy at this
point, but let me just give the URL out
again. So, for people who might be
interested, if you are at Stanford or
UCSF or San Jose State or someplace that
might be able to
help with this type of research. If you
are in a financial position and would
like to support this type of research,
go to tim.blog/cp.
Or if you have other resources you want
to bring to bear on this in some way,
tim.blog/the letters cp standing for
cerebral palsy. So, tim.blog/cp and just
fill out the web form. I'm incredibly
excited about this. We covered a lot in
our first conversation and we've covered
a lot in this conversation.
Is there anything else that you'd like
to mention or cover that we haven't
gotten to already today?
>> Uh
another question.
Well, we covered a lot, but I think one
of the most important, you know, thing
is that
uh people can get help.
And
if we have the right approach, we can
facilitate, create that. And of course,
they change, right?
We didn't change them.
>> Mhm.
>> So, we have to remember that we are
facilitators. We are not really
coaches that, you know,
created that
powerful human being. That actually
powerful human being created themselves.
And we
have to create a place
where it's athletically aligned with our
athleticism and not
care only. We know I say that as soon as
we
care or we exercise without mission or
purpose or goals,
then we can exercise for 10 years and
never change.
>> Mhm.
>> So, I saw these people thousands of
these people.
Right?
So,
it doesn't apply only to cerebral palsy
people cuz it applies to everyone else.
But, with cerebral palsy, it's very
interesting because they have this
situation in the mind in the brain
that actually we could work with.
>> Mhm.
>> These are the patches in the brain that
we can
create the peripheral nervous system
that actually goes around. We can create
that mind. That plasticity of the mind
we can create.
I think it is I have strong feeling that
this is possible. I always believed that
it can be done.
I just created challenges, constant
challenges with the child.
That could deliver
the results to change the way I wanted.
>> Mhm.
>> It has to be always the where are you
going, right? So, for me, he had to walk
straight, he had to walk soft.
And for me, I would not sleep until I
would get it. So, we need devoted
people. We need people that are devoted
to this to these people to help them.
Not just, you know, physical therapists
that want us to take make money and go
home.
>> Mhm.
>> And this is a huge challenge. These
people
extremely challenging and we need to
also challenge them.
>> Yeah.
>> And by the creating this challenge, we
can create amazing thing actually.
>> Yeah.
>> So, it is not something that somebody is
has cancer and it will get worse.
>> Mhm.
>> That's not the situation here. This is a
very unique situation with cerebral
palsy people that we have the situation
that somebody is
and somebody doesn't
change for worse. Somebody is like that.
Can change for worse too because life
happens.
But
because people are like that
we have very
clear slate to begin with.
>> Mhm.
>> And we are not dealing with ill people.
>> Sick people. We just dealing with people
who mechanically something happened to
their brain.
>> Mhm.
>> And that can create for us
a really great beginning.
>> Mhm.
>> And
it could be that with almost any
cerebral palsy
something like this return to
I wouldn't say they cannot return
because many of them
they are just that way.
So, they cannot return anywhere, but
they can improve
and become like Dajan become
Dajan
that is going to
college from the person that
was only
waiting for food and sleep
and couldn't go to toilet
and was lethargic all the time.
The life was like that for him and that
life would be like that.
Right? If nothing happened what actually
we did. He would be that person.
And the parent Here is the parents.
The parents
I saw happy parents.
But after three, four years they
actually they were like a ticking bomb.
You said about intensity between these
three people.
Right?
But about three, four years I saw them
happy first time.
Happy.
And that is enough
to fight for. Right? To give everything
whatever you have. To create
the happiness in these three people who
were worrying all the time.
What will happen
if they die? Or what will happen if
something happened to them? Now they
don't have to worry anymore. The genius
is completely independent. He is in
college for Christ's sake. Just imagine
that. And a lot of that, I believe, 100%
that can happen with everyone.
>> Yeah.
You're the happy body micro progressions
when your philosophy is and philosophy
might scare people off. Your principles
can be applied to so many different
things that you and Aniela have
developed over the years.
Really want to make this research
project happen. So, folks, if you're
interested in any way helping with that
in whatever capacity, you go to
tim.blog/cp.
And then
also want to mention, just like the way
that you and Aniela coach can be applied
almost certainly to many different
conditions, many different
circumstances, all circumstances in some
sense.
I want to give a shout-out to Jeff Wolf,
the director of Prisoner No More. I
always ask everybody before I talk to
them or do anything with them, what
would make it truly a home run. And he
just mentioned the bigger opportunity is
to position Prisoner No More not just as
a stand-alone short, but as a proof of
concept for a larger series.
The vision is a slate under the same
umbrella. So, you could have Prisoner No
More for alcoholism, Prisoner No More
for fill in the blank, right? Which I
think is also very exciting. So, I
really, really hope people You got to
watch it. You got to see what we're
talking about visually. It'll just
A lot of you are going to cry. I'm going
to tell you in advance. But, it's good
cry. So, check it out.
tim.blog/hardchoices
in honor of
>> Hard choices.
>> Hard choices, easy life. Easy choices,
hard life. So, so it's
tim.blog/hardchoices.
Check it out. You can find the Happy
Body and more on Jerzy and Aniela's
training at the happybody.com.
And I'll link to everything in the show
notes as usual at tim.blog/podcast.
So,
if you're like, that's a lot to
remember, don't worry about it. Just go
to tim.blog/podcast
and search Jerzy, not spelled like New
Jersey, but spelled j e r z y.
And trust me, there's only one Jerzy on
my website. It's Jerzy Gregorek.
Jerzy, thank you so much for the time.
It's always great to see you.
>> Thank you, Tim.
>> And
everybody who has tuned in, as always, I
appreciate you.
Till next time, be just a bit kinder
than is necessary
to others and to yourself. But,
not just comfort. Don't just make
yourself feel better. Don't just eat
that cheeseburger
and watch reality TV on Netflix.
Challenge yourself. Wherever you happen
to be, you can make progress. You can
make amazing progress. You You just need
to right starting point. And for that
reason, check out the happybody.com.
Listen to my first conversation with
Jerzy on the podcast as well. Until next
time, thanks for tuning in.
>> Thank you, Tim.